Guide to the Mona Jimenez and Gina Murtagh Papers from a Documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers TAM.839
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mona Jimenez and Gina Murtagh Papers from a Documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers
1989-1997
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jimenez, Mona
Vagabond Puppeteers
TAM.839
3.5 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes
10 Hi8
28 U-matic
The Vagabond Puppeteers were a traveling puppet theater who were inspired by leftists campaigns in rural Mexico to educate the people of Mexico in the post-revolutionary era. Members included Harriet Holtzman, Mary Walton Jimenez, Jerry Oberwager, and Pete Seeger. The troupe toured New York State in the summer of 1939, with the goal of supporting the labor organizing of the Dairy Farmers Union, who at the time were on strike and agitating for higher prices. In the late 1980s and 1990s, Mona Jimenez and Gina Murtagh planned, researched, and recorded footage for an unfinished documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers. The Mona Jimenez and Gina Murtagh Papers from a Documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers (dated 1989-1997) consists of materials created and collected by Jimenez and Murtagh while researching and creating an unfinished documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers. Materials include research and planning documents, including correspondence, release forms, research files, and tape logs. The majority of the collection consists of video recordings on Hi8 and U-Matic videocassette. The recordings include interviews with the four members of the Vagabond Puppeteers, Holtzman; Jimenez; Oberwager; and Seeger, during which they describe their experiences in the performance troupe as well as the political environment they were engaged with. Other recordings document a reunion of the Puppeteers at Oberwager's home in 1991. The collection also includes recordings of Jimenez and Murtagh's efforts to locate people active with the Dairy Farmers Union, dairy farming in the 1930s, farming in the 1980s and early 1990s more generally, or who may have recalled attending a Puppeteers performance during the summer tour of 1939. The collection documents not only the Vagabond Puppeteers and their approach to political art in the 1930s, but also the connections between labor organizing and radical art.
Scope and Contents
The Mona Jimenez and Gina Murtagh Papers from a Documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers (dated 1989-1997) consists of materials created and collected by Jimenez and Murtagh while researching and creating an unfinished documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers. Materials include research and planning documents, including correspondence, release forms, research files, and tape logs. The majority of the collection consists of video recordings on Hi8 and U-Matic videocassette. The recordings include interviews with the four members of the Vagabond Puppeteers, Harriet Holtzman; Mary Walton Jimenez; Jerry Oberwager; and Pete Seeger, during which they describe their experiences in the performance troupe as well as the political environment they were engaged with. Other recordings document a reunion of the Puppeteers at Oberwager's home in 1991. The collection also includes recordings of Jimenez and Murtagh's efforts to locate people active with the Dairy Farmers' Union, dairy farming in the 1930s, farming in the 1980s and early 1990s more generally, or who may have recalled attending a Puppeteers performance during the summer tour of 1939. The collection documents not only the Vagabond Puppeteers and their approach to political art in the 1930s, but also the connections between labor organizing and radical art.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mona Jimenez in June 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.043.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Other Finding Aids
Detailed descriptions of audiovisual items are available through the collection file by request.
Historical Note on the Vagabond Puppeteers
The Vagabond Puppeteers were a traveling puppet theater who were inspired by leftists campaigns in rural Mexico to educate the people of Mexico in the post-revolutionary era. Members included Harriet Holtzman, Mary Walton Jimenez, Jerry Oberwager, and Pete Seeger. The troupe toured New York State in the summer of 1939, with the goal of supporting the labor organizing of the Dairy Farmers Union, who at the time were on strike and agitating for higher prices. The Vagabond Puppeteers and their brand of political theater had influences on more contemporary activist theater like Bread and Roses and Theatre of the Oppressed.
Biographical Note on Mona Jimenez
Mona Jimenez is a conservator and video preservation educator and consultant whose work focuses on the preservation of independent media and media art. She served as the Associate Director and Associate Arts Professor at the Moving Image Archiving and Preservation program at New York University from 2013-2017. She is also the daughter of Mary Walton Jiménez, one of the members of the Vagabond Puppeteers. In the late 1980s and 1990s, Jimenez and Gina Murtagh planned, researched, and recorded footage for an unfinished documentary about the Vagabond Puppeteers.
Puppet theater.; Puppeteers; Radical theater; Theater -- Political aspects.; Art and social action; Art -- Political aspects.; Politics in art.; Labor unions -- Organizing.; Labor movement.; Strikes and lockouts.; Documentary films--Production and direction; Jimenez, Mona; Dairy Farmers' Union; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Jiménez, Mary Rachel Walton; Oberwager, Jerry; Holtzman, Harriet
- Documentary Planning Materials -- Research Files, Research Forms; Tape Logs, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-24)
- Documentary Planning Materials -- Research Files, Research Forms; Tape Logs; Photographs, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
- Interview with Pete Seeger, One of the Four Vagabond Puppeteers, Canadaigua, NY, circa 1991
  - Part 1, cuid43206 (Box 5, U-matic 839.016)
  - Part 2, cuid43207 (Box 5, U-matic 839.017)
  - Part 3, cuid43208 (Box 5, U-matic 839.018)
- Interview with Albert (Al) Kuchler Boonville, NY., undated
  - Part 1, cuid43209 (Box 5, U-matic 839.013)
  - Part 2, cuid43210 (Box 6, U-matic 839.019)
  - Part 3, cuid43211 (Box 6, U-matic 839.020)
  - Part 4, cuid43212 (Box 7, U-matic 839.025)
- Interview with Mary Walton Jimenez, Chapel Hill, NY, undated
  - Part 1, cuid43213 (Box 7, U-matic 839.026)
  - Part 2, cuid43214 (Box 7, U-matic 839.038)
  - Part 3, cuid43215 (Box 6, U-matic 839.021)
- Interview with Harriet Holtzman Lansky and Jerry Oberwager, Two of the Four Vagabond Puppeteers, Great Neck (?), NY, undated
  - Part 1, cuid43216 (Box 6, U-matic 839.022)
  - Part 1, cuid43217 (Box 6, U-matic 839.023)
  - Part 2, cuid43218 (Box 6, U-matic 839.024)
  - Part 3, cuid43219 (Box 7, U-matic 839.027)
- Reunion of Four Vagabond Puppeteers in Great Neck, NY. Followed by Footage of Seneca Lake, NY and Photographs Unrelated to the Vagabond Puppeteers, 1988-08-05 (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Hi8 839.033)
- Interview with Josephine Gips, Poolville, NY., 1994-08-12
  - Video Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Hi8 839.034)
  - Video Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Hi8 839.035)
- Interview with Michael and Eleanor Pupko, Boonville, NY, 1990-01-20
  - Part 1, cuid43220 (Box 3, U-matic 839.001)
  - Part 2, cuid43221 (Box 3, U-matic 839.002)
  - Part 3, cuid43222 (Box 3, U-matic 839.003)
  - Part 4, cuid43223 (Box 3, U-matic 839.004)
- Interview with Roman Charney, Boonville, NY, Part 2, 1990-01-29; cuid43224 (Box 3, U-matic 839.005)
- Interviews with Roman Charney, Part 2 and Carol Seelman, Boonville, NY, 1990-01-29; cuid43225 (Box 3, U-matic 839.006)
- Interview with Bruce King, Boonville, NY, 1990-01-28; cuid43226 (Box 4, U-matic 839.007)
- Boonville, NY, 1990-01-28; cuid43227 (Box 4, U-matic 839.008)
- Boonville, NY, 1990-01-28; cuid43228 (Box 4, U-matic 839.009)
- Tape 1 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform. Interview with Marion Hammerle, Daughter-in-Law of a Farmer Who was Active in the DFU and Left Home for Several Weeks While They Were on Strike. Part 1 of Interview with Ray Adamson, Dairy Farmer Organizing for Fair Prices in 1991., 1991-08 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Hi8 839.032)
- Tape 2 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform. Part 2 of Interview with Ray Adamson, Current Dairy Farmer Organizing for Fair Prices. Interview with Rush O. French, a Young Man Living on a Farm in 1939., 1991-08 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Hi8 839.031)
- Tape 3 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform. Interview with Alvin Alsip and [unknown] Alsip. Walking to Alsip's farm. Team Update at Home of Marshall Aungier. Part 2 of Interview with --Coye (19-)., 1991-08 (Box Shared Tamiment 098, Hi8 839.029)
- Tape 4 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform. Part 2 of Interview with --Coye (19-).Interview with Peter Erancieur (19-). Part 1 of interview with Leonard (Leo) Dwyer and Winifred Dywer (19--)., 1991-08 (Box Shared Tamiment 098, Hi8 839.028)
- Tape 5 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform. Part 2 of Interview with Leonard (Leo) Dwyer and Winifred Dywer, 1991-08-23 (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Hi8 839.037)
- Tape 6 of Road Trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform, 1991-08 (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Hi8 839.036)
- Tape 7 of Road trip to Find Members of Dairy Farmers Union (DFU) and Those Who May Have Seen the Vagabond Puppeteers Perform, 1991-08-25 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Hi8 839.030)
- Protection Copies of Road Trip Tape Segments, undated
  - Video Recording, undated; cuid43229 (Box 4, U-matic 839.010)
  - Video Recording, undated; cuid43230 (Box 4, U-matic 839.011)
  - Video Recording, undated; cuid43231 (Box 4, U-matic 839.012)
  - Video Recording, undated; cuid43232 (Box 4, U-matic 839.014)
  - Video Recording, undated; cuid43233 (Box 5, U-matic 839.015)
- Hi8 Transfers, TW_TAM_839_ER_1